A Finding Aid to the William P. Daley Papers, 1905-2016 (bulk 1951-2001), in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
William P. Daley papers
1905-2016
bulk 1951-2001
Archives of American Art
Daley, William, 1925-2002
AAA.dalewill
Archival Resource Key
26.3 Linear feet
The papers of ceramist William P. Daley measure 26.3 linear feet and date from 1905-2016 (bulk 1951-2001). The collection documents Daley's career as both artist and teacher through biographical information, correspondence, exhibition files, project files, material on workshops, seminars, and lectures, teaching files, artist files, reference files, printed material, photographs, financial files, and artwork. There is an 11.1 linear foot unprocessed addition to this collection donated in 2022 that includes project, exhibition and book files; photographs and slides of works of art, Daley and events; printed material; writings; awards and honors; lectures; drawings; kiln logs; notebooks; audio cassettes, CDs and DVDs; files on artists and miscellany regarding William P. Daley. Materials date from circa 1959-2016.
Biographical Note
Born in Hastings-on-Hudson, New York, in 1925, William P. Daley developed an interest in art at an early age, and was encouraged by his parents William and Alice. In 1943 Daley finished high school and enlisted in the Army Air Corps. When the war ended, he returned home, and with the help of the G.I. Bill, completed a B.S. in Art Education from Massachusetts College of Art, and a M.A. from the Teachers College at Columbia University. While at the Massachusetts College of Art he met and married fellow student Catherine Stennes. They had three children together, Barbara, Charlotte, and Thomas.
Originally intending to focus on painting, Daley discovered his love for ceramics while in art school. Much of his early work after graduation consisted of architectural and sculptural commissions. From 1961 to 1965 he held teaching positions as a ceramics instructor at the University of Northern Iowa, State University of New York at New Paltz, Philadelphia College of Art and Design, and the State University of New York at Fredonia. In 1965 he settled in Elkins Park, Pennsylvania and returned to the Philadelphia College of Art and Design, University of the Arts. There he taught in both the Industrial Design and Craft Department until his retirement from the college in 1990. When not teaching in the classroom, and even after retirement, Daley traveled extensively giving workshops and lectures at art centers, high schools, colleges, and universities. He has won several awards for teaching in the arts, including the College Art Association of America Distinguished Teaching of Art Award in 1991.
Daley became an active member of the crafts movement in Philadelphia, co-founding the Philadelphia Council of Professional Craftsmen. The Helen Drutt Gallery opened in Philadelphia in 1974 and gave Daley his first one man show there. Later, the gallery would become Daley's primary dealer. A self-proclaimed "mud man" and maker of "cosmic pots," Daley has focused throughout his career on the issues of the ceramic vessel, using drawings to explore his ideas. In 1994 the Renwick Gallery held a retrospective entitled, "William Daley: Ceramic Works and Drawings" which featured thirty years of his work. William Daley continued producing new work until his death in 2022.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of ceramist William Daley measure 26.3 linear feet and date from 1905-2016 (bulk 1951-2001). The collection documents Daley's career as both artist and teacher through biographical information, correspondence, exhibition files, project files, material on workshops, seminars, and lectures, teaching files, artist files, reference files, printed material, photographs, financial files, and artwork.
Biographical files encompass items from Daley's early life including family, education, and military materials, as well as files on awards he has earned, and interviews he has given during his career. Correspondence includes general correspondence with family, friends, artists, colleagues, and schools, as well as named files on correspondence with galleries, organizations, and individuals. The largest series in the collection, Exhibition Files, spanning a fifty year period, contain materials on group and solo exhibitions in which Daley participated, and also includes Auction Files and Exhibition Juror Files. Project Files contain materials related to public and private commissions.
Workshops, Seminars, and Lectures, documents the numerous events at which Daley taught or spoke on topics of art, ceramics, and/or education. Many of these topics are also found in Writings, which include drafts of writings by Daley and others. Within this series Daley's personal address lists and calendars are also found. The Teaching Files provide insight into Daley's teaching methods, primarily at the Philadelphia College of Art, from materials such as curriculum plans, lesson notes, and assignments. Also within this series are general teaching notes which contain many hand drawn diagrams. The Artist Files that Daley created house materials concerning artists who were friends, former students, co-workers, and colleagues. Daley also compiled Reference Files containing materials on various topics for use in teaching and projects. Topics include the art of various countries, formulas and tables for ceramics, essays on art and education, and other general subjects. Printed Material provides information, primarily on ceramics, through press clippings, exhibit announcements, catalogs and journals, as well as other miscellaneous materials. Also found are reviews of Daley's work. While photographs are included throughout the collection, the Photographs series contains additional photographs of Daley in the studio or in the classroom, as well as photographs of artwork by others. Also found in the collection are copies of drawings Daley completed throughout his career.
There is an 11.1 linear foot unprocessed addition to this collection donated in 2022 that includes project, exhibition and book files; photographs and slides of works of art, Daley and events; printed material; writings; awards and honors; lectures; drawings; kiln logs; notebooks; audio cassettes, CDs and DVDs; files on artists and miscellany regarding William P. Daley. Materials date from circa 1959-2016.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into fourteen series. Each series is arranged either in rough chronological or alphabetical order.
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Files, 1905-2003 (Box 1; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1957-2001, undated (Boxes 1-2; 1.5 linear feet)
Series 3: Exhibition Files, 1949-1999, undated (Boxes 3-5; 2.7 linear feet)
Series 4: Project Files, 1956-2000 (Boxes 5-6; 1.0 linear foot)
Series 5: Workshops, Seminars, and Lectures, 1958-1998, undated, (Boxes 6-8; 2.3 linear feet)
Series 6: Writings, 1951-2003, undated (Box 9; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 7: Teaching Files, 1951-1998, undated (Boxes 9-10; 1.3 linear feet)
Series 8: Artist Files, 1938-2001, undated (Boxes 10-12; 2.1 linear feet)
Series 9: Reference Files, 1951-2001, undated (Box 13; 1.0 linear foot)
Series 10: Printed Material, 1936-2004 (Boxes 14-15; 1.9 linear feet)
Series 11: Photographs, 1953-2001, undated (Box 15; 5 folders)
Series 12: Financial Files, 1962-1997, undated (Box 16; 4 folders)
Series 13: Artwork, 1954-2003, undated (Boxes 15-16; 3 folders)
Series 14: Unprocessed Addition, circa 1959-2016 (Boxes 17-27; OV 28)
Provenance
The William P. Daley papers were donated by William Daley in 2003 and by Thomas Daley in 2022.
Restrictions on Access
This collection is temporarily closed to researchers due to archival processing. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Potters; Transcripts; Drawings; Pottery -- Study and teaching -- Pennsylvania; Photographs; Art -- Study and teaching; Sculptors -- Pennsylvania; Glazes -- Formulae; Ceramicists; Interviews; Pottery; Philadelphia College of Art -- Faculty; Chihuly, Dale, 1941-; Schreckengost, Viktor, 1906-; Nanette L. Laitman Documentation Project for Craft and Decorative Arts in America; Howard, Robert Boardman, 1896-1983
- Biographical Files, 1905-2003, undated; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes artist statements, a brief biography and professional history of Daley, as well as school and military records. It also contains files on William Daley's Honorary Doctorates and numerous other awards and typically include correspondence, brochures, and other related materials concerning the awards. Also found are documents associated with Daley's family, including correspondence with his parents during World War II and materials on his father, William Joseph Daley. There are files on two oral history interviews including a 120 page interview of Daley conducted in 1985 by the Columbia University American Craftspeople Oral History Project. This series is arranged alphabetically by type of material and chronologically under each heading. Most materials prior to 1950 are photocopies.
  - Artist Statements, 1956, 1997, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Awards, National Council on Education for the Ceramic Arts Honorary Membership, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Awards, State University of New York Research Foundation Grant-In-Aid Award, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Awards, American Institute of Architects Craftsmanship Medal Award Nomination, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Awards, National Endowment for the Arts Craftsmen's Fellowship Grant, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Awards, Massachusetts College of Art Outstanding Achievement Award, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Awards, Philadelphia College of Art Venture Fund, 1984-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Awards, American Craft Council's College of Fellows, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Awards, University of the Arts, University Professor of the Arts, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Awards, College Art Association Distinguished Teaching of Art Award, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Awards, Art Matters' Lifetime Achievement Award, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Awards, PEW Fellowship Nomination, 1991-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Awards, Interior Design Council's Roland A. Gallimore Memorial Award, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Awards, Massachusetts College of Art Distinguished Alumnus 1994, 1993-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Awards, American Craft Council Aileen Osborn Webb 2003 Gold Medal, Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Biography/Professional History, 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Birth and Baptismal Certificates, 1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Education, School Records, 1941-1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Education, High School Artwork, 1942, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Education, Letters of Recommendation, 1943, 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Education, Massachusetts School of Art Records, 1948-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Education, Acceptance Letter from Radcliffe College, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Education, Teachers College, Columbia University Records, 1950-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Family, William Joseph Daley Materials, 1905, 1919, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Family, Correspondence with Parents During War, 1944, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Honorary Doctorate, Maine College of Art, 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Honorary Doctorate, Philadelphia College of Art and Design, 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Interview, Fine Arts Brochure, 1979-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Interview, Columbia University American Craftspeople Oral History Project, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Military, Service Records, 1943-1950, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Military, Veterans Administration Records, 1945-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Correspondence, 1957-2001, undated; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  This series contains both personal and professional correspondence. A significant amount of correspondence related to William Daley's professional career is also located within series 3, 4, and 5, and correspondence with certain artists is found in the Artist Files in Series 8.
  Arrangement note
  The Correspondence Files are arranged into two subseries:
  2.1: General Correspondence, 1957-2001, undated
  2.2: Named Files, 1959-2000, undated
  - General Correspondence, 1957-2001, undated; 2.1; Archival Resource Key
    General Correspondence primarily consists of letters of a more personal nature from family, friends, artists, and colleagues, including numerous cards and postcards. Also within are requests from galleries, schools, universities, and art associations for Daley to take part in exhibitions or workshops. Files are arranged chronologically by year.
    - General Correspondence, 1957-1985, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33-51)
    - General Correspondence, 1986-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-27)
  - Named Files, 1959-2000, undated; 2.2; Archival Resource Key
    Named Files are arranged alphabetically by the correspondents name and contain primarily professional correspondence to and from Daley. Included are files on galleries, such as Exhibit A and Garth Clark Gallery, and several councils and organizations in which Daley was a member. There are also files on individuals with whom Daley exchanged a significant amount of correspondence over a long period of time. Most notable is Helen Drutt, owner of the Helen Drutt Gallery which represents Daley's artwork.
    - American Crafts Council, 1976-1979, 1993-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Art Advisory Council, Wills Eye Hospital, 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Bates, Wayne, 1979-1982, 1990-1998, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Braunstein Gallery, 1980-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Bryant, Keith, 1987-1993, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Busch, Gail, 1982-1995, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Ceramics Monthly, 1979-1980, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Colburn, Anthony, 1990-1992, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Drutt, Helen, 1979-2000, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Exhibit A, 1977-1985, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 37-38)
    - Garth Clark Gallery, 1978-1991, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Larsen, Jack Lenor, 1982-1994, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Levin, Elaine, 1979-1990, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Martha Schneider Gallery, Inc., 1987-1988, Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Nelson, Glenn C., 1959, 1968-1984, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - New York State College of Ceramics, 1965, 1980-1984, Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Philadelphia Council of Professional Craftsmen, 1966, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - The Renzetti Fund, 1981-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Wolf, Howard A., 1978-1987, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Exhibition Files, 1949-1999, undated; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 2.7 Linear feet Boxes 3-5
  The Exhibition Files are organized into three subseries:
  3.1: Exhibition Files, 1949-1998, undated
  3.2: Auction Files, 1979-1993, undated
  3.3: Exhibition Juror Files, 1968-1999
  - Exhibition Files, 1949-1998, undated; 3.1; Archival Resource Key
    Exhibition Files contain material on the numerous group and solo exhibits in which William Daley participated. Files typically include correspondence, expense lists and receipts, price lists, and printed materials, including brochures, catalogs, announcements, and press clippings. A few files also contain photographs. Files are arranged chronologically by year of exhibition.
    - New England Painting and Sculpture (1949), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Decorative Arts and Ceramics Exhibition, 1949, 1952-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - "Craftsmen of the Midwestern College Art Conference" (1952), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Iowa Artists Show, 1952-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Blackhawk County Art Show, 1952-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Iowa State Teachers College Invitational (1953), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Fiber, Clay, Metal 1953 Craft Competition, Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - American Craftsman's Educational Council, Young Americans 1954, Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - American Craftsman's Educational Council, Young Americans 1955, Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - New York Society of Ceramic Arts 61st Annual Exhibition (1955), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - New Paltz Craft Cooperative Shop (1956), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Fifth Annual Miami National Ceramic Exhibition (1957), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Pace Gallery, circa 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Philadelphia Art Alliance 46th Season (1960), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Everson Museum of Art 22nd Ceramic National (1962), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Scripps College Twentieth Annual Invitational Ceramic Exhibition (1964), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Sculpture, Ceramics, Drawings: Old Main Gallery (1965), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Gallery 1015 (1966), 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Penn State Exhibition (1966), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - 24th Ceramic National (1966), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Craftsmen '67, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - First Survey of Contemporary American Crafts, University of Texas (1967), 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Ceramic Design, Philadelphia Art Alliance (1967), 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - 25th Ceramic National, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Fourth National Invitational Craft Exhibition (1968), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Artists Equity Exhibition (1968), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - "Ceramics by William Daley" (1969), 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Drawing Exhibition at Beaver College (1969), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Craftsmen '70, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - CRAFTS 1970, Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Craftsmen '73, circa 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - University of New Mexico Invitational Craft Exhibition, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - William Daley at Helen Drutt Gallery (1974), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Clay U.S.A. (1975), 1975-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - "Philadelphia: Three Centuries of American Art" (1976), 1975-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Exhibition of Liturgical Arts (1976), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - William Daley at the Helen Drutt Gallery (1976), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Soup Tureens: 1976, Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Contemporary Clay: Ten Approaches (1976), 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Millersville State College 5th Annual Clay Invitational (1977), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - The Philadelphia Craft Show (1977), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Vessel as Metaphor (1977), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Art in Service of Liturgy (1978), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Artists Equity Triennial Exhibition (1978), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Century of Ceramics in the United States 1878-1978, 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 45-46)
    - "Wayne Bates, William Daley, Richard Reinhardt" (1978), 1978-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - "William P. Daley: Ceramic Sculpture at Braunstein Gallery" (1979), 1978-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Central Iowa Art Association Ceramic Study Collection, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Fiber, Clay, & Metal (1979), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - "Invitational Clay/Fiber/Metal Exhibition" (1979), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Olaf Skoogfors: 20th Century Goldsmith (1979), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - The Contemporary American Potter (1980), 1979-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 53-54)
    - Philadelphia: Clay 1980, 1979-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Contemporary Ceramics: A Response to Wedgewood (1980), 1979-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - William P. Daley Ceramics at Helen Drutt Gallery (1980), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Celebrate Haystack, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - American Potters I and II (1981), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - William Daley: Recent Works at Exhibit A (1981), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Skidmore College Fifth National Crafts Invitational (1981), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - East Coast Vessels, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Who's Afraid of American Pottery? (1983), 1981-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 63-64)
    - William Daley at the Massachusetts College of Art (1982), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 65-66)
    - Philadelphia College of Art: Inside/Outside (1982), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Mankato State University Invitational, 1982-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - "Art in Craft Media" (1983), Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - New Works in Clay by William Daley, Elsa Rady, Betty Woodman, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Affects/Effects 2 (1983), Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - American Clay Artists: Philadelphia '83, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Ceramic Echoes: Historical References in Contemporary Ceramics (1983), Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - William P. Daley at the Helen Drutt Gallery (1983), Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Works on Paper (1983), Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Clay in New Mexico '83, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - "A Salute to Pennsylvania's Artistic Heritage" (1983), Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - "Skidmore Craft Invitational '84", 1983-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Clay Vessels (1984), Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - U.S. News and World Report (1984), Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - "Continental Insurance 1984: The Continental Collection", Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - William Daley at Alfred University (1985), 1984-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Bill Daley at Garth Clark Gallery (1985), 1984-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 13)